Milling Family papers, Inclusive: 1852-1997, undated, Bulk: 1860-1867
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Milling Family papers
Inclusive: 1852-1997, undated, Bulk: 1860-1867
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
3621
Milling family
1 document box
The Milling Family Papers primarily contain correspondence between members of the Milling family around and during the American Civil War. Financial documents and a copy of a 1997 issue of Confederate Veteran are also included.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
David Milling (1797-1867), a native of County Down, Northern Ireland, owned a plantation in Fairfield County, South Carolina. He and his first wife (probably a cousin), Jane Wright Milling Milling (1806-1847), had six children together: John R. Milling (1825-1864), Dr. James S. Milling (1831- 1895), David Y. Milling, Jr. (1833-1895), Thomas H. Milling (born 1840), William Milling (born 1842), and Margaret Milling (born 1844). Jane Wright Milling Milling died in 1847.
David Milling later married Sarah Yongue Milling (1823-1893). David and Sarah Milling had five children together: Robert Russell Milling (1844-1893), Andrew Yongue Milling (1851-1909), Mary Agnes Milling Lemmon (1854-1934), G. Ladson H. Milling (1860-1935), Lenora E. Milling Macfie (1864-1936).
Two of Milling’s sons, David Y. Milling, Jr. and John Milling, moved to Texas prior to the Civil War. They settled in Anderson County, Texas. These two, plus William, all served in the American Civil War on the Confederate side. John R. and William Milling both enlisted in Company D, 6th South Carolina Infantry, John as a 1st Lieutenant and William as a sergeant. John, a soldier in the Boyce Guards of the 6th South Carolina Infantry, died in the war in 1864.
James S. Milling studied at the Medical College of South Carolina until 1854 and married his cousin Mary (1828-1913) in 1857. Two years later he moved his plantation to Bossier Parish, Louisiana. Throughout the American Civil War, Mary and their children stayed in South Carolina, but moved to Louisiana in 1866.
Scope and Content
The Milling Family Papers consist of family correspondence and financial documents from 1852 to 1873. Letters primarily concern plantation life and relations between plantation owners and slaves both prior to and during the Civil War, the secession of South Carolina, enlistment into the Confederate Army of all of Dr. Milling's brothers, John's death at the attack of Fort Harrison, General William Tecumseh Sherman's march through South Carolina, the surrender of the Confederate Army, and the attitudes of Southerners to emancipation. Letters after the Civil War primarily concern relationships between plantation owners and freedmen. A 1997 copy of Confederate Veteran with an article about James A. Milling is also included. The bulk of the correspondence is to Dr. James S. Milling from his father, David Milling, and the bulk of the financial documents relate to business (especially medical) affairs of Dr. James S. Milling. The correspondence is primarily between members living in Bossier Parish, Louisiana; Anderson County, Texas; and Fairfield County, South Carolina.
Arrangement
The Milling Family Papers contain three series: I. Correspondence, II. Financial Documents, and III. Printed Materials. All series are arranged chronologically. The Printed Materials series contains only one item.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 3621. Acquired 2004-06-09
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Confederate States of America. Army.
Places
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Correspondence.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.
Subjects
Financial records.; Periodicals.; Plantation life -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Plantation owners -- 19th century -- Correspondence.; Secession -- South Carolina -- 1860-1870 -- Correspondence.; Sherman's March through the Carolinas -- Correspondence.; Slavery — America -- Correspondence.; Slaves — Emancipation -- Southern states -- Public opinion — History -- 19th century -- Correspondence.
Genres
Correspondence.
- Correspondence, 1852-1869; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  Arranged chronologically. Letters among members of the Milling family around and during the time of the American Civil War.
  - Correspondence, 1852-1853 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1854-1856 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1861 January-July (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1861 August-December (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1863 January-June (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1863 July-December (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1864 January-May (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1864 June-December (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1865 January-May (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1865 June-December (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1866-1869 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Financial Documents, 1857-1873, undated; 2
  Arranged chronologically. Contracts, receipts, and other financial documents from around the time of the American Civil War.
  - Financial Documents, 1857-1868 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Financial Documents, 1869-1873, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Printed Materials, 1997; 3
  One Confederate Veteran magazine from 1997 with article about James A. Milling.
  - Printed Materials, Confederate Veteran magazine, Volume Six, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 17)